to
welcome to crossing face where christian
and muslim talk religion and politics
really multi-faith people talk about
religion and politics and then uh
matthew hawkings uh is on hiatus uh he
went in for a
heart checkup and he two days later he
was in open heart surgery so he's
recovering
uh
there's some question of whether or not
it was the heart surgery or my prayers
that healed him we don't know yet but uh
i'm gonna go on a little bit of both but
i think the prayers weighed heavier
because ishmaeli prayers are are uh
weighed very very heavy with uh the
almighty allah and and uh god or
whatever you're calling them these days
so
our my good friend john kiriyaku who's
uh going to sit with me and talk about
the current unpleasantness in
afghanistan uh as everyone knows this is
an issue near and dear to me i i we've
spent the last week
going from
uh
uh facilitating visas to get to the
airport to stay safe and stay alive at
least that's been my
um
my uh my journey this week uh now we're
moving from the tactical of trying to
figure out what's going on
at the airport and in kabul and
afghanistan to some of the policy in dc
i'm presently in washington
engaging different agencies and the
executive branch to try to give them
some advice
but we wanted to sit down and talk with
my friend here because both operated in
theater in
central and south asia
and there's been a lot of experts uh out
there um i don't claim to be and i i
know that john doesn't claim to be an
expert but we do know a lot about the
region and i don't think there's anybody
who's an expert in afghanistan uh i
would argue this more you learn the more
you learn that you don't know and it
doesn't matter if you're from the region
or you have afghan blood the the
the challenge is is that it's such an
amorphous environment dynamic
environment um but also there's uh such
a rich history uh and also a rich amount
of current events that lead to someone
to uh uh
the conclusion that there's so much that
needs to be that needs to be said about
it needs to be uh noodled over and it
takes a team of people to do it so
in this case we're here to talk about
the taliban and we're going to talk a
little bit about the origins because
john and i spoke a little bit earlier
about how there's so much that's not
known
about the taliban and their origins and
their role in afghanistan um and uh we
thought that it would be appropriate for
us to have this conversation welcome
john
thank you good to be back with you yeah
it's always good to see your face you
know so
uh
it's one of these moments in time where
we we only seem to talk about the
something that's current new and
terrible yes
that's every conversation we have yeah
so um but uh so original taliban i i i
give you my 30 seconds that i usually
tell people i usually say look you have
a
a the majority of the after the uh the
soviet war uh as this we supported the
mujahideen in the united states as the
soviet work came to a close gene
mujahideen was
essentially
roving around the country committing all
kinds of acts uh criminal acts um some
of the first
uh
issues that happened um were uh
mujahideen attacking civilians and
raping girls and the taliban started
started to
their profile started to increase as
vigilantes someone that would hunt down
mujahideen fighters right and and bring
them to justice which is street justice
you know hang them high type stuff
and so
as
this struggle continued in the 90s
the taliban's support grew and their
numbers grew and eventually you had
vigilantes that took over the seat of
government
uh and i don't know how you would feel
but i'm a big comic book reader so
batman love him but wouldn't want him to
be the mayor of my town and wouldn't
want him to be at the seat of government
and so that characterizes at least from
my perspective the taliban in
in afghanistan particularly in the 90s
and heading towards the the afghan war
um and and one consideration is that
they the the the taliban is
on everybody talks about the pakistani
taliban is it's it largely the recruits
are largely the population from the
pashtuns which is which is you know they
saddle the border between afghanistan
and
and pakistan so
and this is uh goes back to my whole
theory that 90 percent of the problems
in the world are are british made you
know they have the british you know so
that that line that borders from the
brits but how what's your perspective on
the origins of the taliban uh up to the
up to the afghan war and and then maybe
we can talk about their role uh
during uh after 9 11 and then we can get
to some of the current events yeah
everything that you've said uh is true
uh there's there's even more background
that to me is very interesting and that
is when the soviets invaded afghanistan
it caused a refugee crisis and many many
afghan families crossed the border into
pakistan they they raised their children
there they had children there and many
of those children were educated in
madrasas religious schools well
the pakistani government was having a
problem
with
with mujahideen
um pirating essentially trucks as they
were crossing
as pakistani trucks were crossing into
afghanistan on their way to iran to sell
goods
and so benazir bhutto was the prime
minister of pakistan at the time she
came up with this idea or her people
came up with this idea that they would
take students
taliban the plural of talib student
take taliban out of the madrasas and
have them ride along with these truck
drivers to protect them you know just a
talib with an ak-47 to protect them as
they as they crossed afghanistan to sell
their goods in iran riding shotgun
riding shotgun exactly and it worked and
then somebody said well this this
program is working maybe it would be
more effective maybe it would be more
cost effective even if instead of having
the right shotgun in the trucks we just
place them in in villages along the
highway
and so they did that
and as
vigilantes you know now they're on the
ground
uh bringing their own brand of law and
order to these in their arms they're on
the ground
and they're armed and they had popular
support because they were all about law
and order
and the next thing you know they begin
to take over villages and then
territories and then regions uh we get
into the late 1990s and they take the
whole of afghanistan and that was the
origin of the taliban
it's it's interesting because a lot of
people don't know that they actually had
popular support that there was
uh
they were the party of law and order and
in in an era in a you know in a
post-soviet
uh war-torn country uh with
you know a lot of armed
militias floating around it was it may
have been a relevant time or relevant
period for a group like this to to take
over or to establish order even though
their rigidness was there and this is
not a taliban sympathetic sort of thing
but it it it was they were they were
they were the entity for the time and
they fulfilled a need and there could
have been uh something else that was
there i mean we i talk a lot about
policy in in afghanistan and maybe if we
didn't draw down and and leave and lock
stock and barrel um we could have
figured out a path for the mujahideen to
uh address the human rights issues and
present and establish the seat of
government and go from there because it
was the communists after the three years
right three years after the yes this was
a big mistake that was made in
washington that once the soviets were
were pushed out of afghanistan we just
decided that our work was done there and
instead of financing things like schools
or physical plant you know
sewage processing facilities or
electrical grids or whatever we just
went home
and then figured that was the end of it
in fact that wasn't the end of it and
you raised an important point that i
want to i want to talk about too and
that is the fact that the taliban are
not foreign interlopers they're not
occupiers they're not an invasion force
they're afghans yeah and so so many
americans question well why didn't
afghans take up arms against the uh the
taliban well because they're also
afghans right and the and people in in
villages were having a problem with
crime they were having a problem with
piracy and with
soviet troops and you know crimes
against women
they welcomed that law and order i think
that's something that many americans
most americans don't understand well
also you have for thousands of years you
have these infl we call in the west
informal systems but they're very formal
systems to afghans right and in in
theater so and and you were talking
about border crossings generally there
was this there's a tribe there's a group
called the arbi right and they would be
in charge of all the border crossings
and it'd be one of these things where
this tribe generated revenue
from
assuring beginning payment from people
that were crossing the border
so uh and i you're you're familiar with
the arbitrage right they they cost
us right so if you didn't pay them
something probably would happen they
would get their payment one way or
another as you were crossing the border
and traveling down those passes right
those systems
were in jeopardy or or
um were
teetering after the soviet rule right um
and they were being re-established right
these tribes were reaffirming themselves
and the revenues were
slowly starting to to build and it was
very mature up to 911 but then after the
invasion the arbokai
there was there was a during the karzai
you know regime there was a lot of uh
um
no people nobody really understood the
informal systems but then on top of that
they started to establish border control
like in the united states and so these
tribes became disenfranchised and didn't
have a revenue source and so what
happened to these people and maybe you
could talk a little bit about that
because that
is a vacuum that that the taliban now
has really carp launched to film
yeah see this is another thing that
americans don't understand
these systems seem so primitive to us
but they worked you know it's like the
hawala system that so many people in the
region use for banking or for
transferring money it works we don't
like it
we have a name for it walk through the
whole hola system so so people
understand sure uh while the system is a
way of sending money where you either
don't have access to banks or you don't
trust banks let's say you need to send
fifty dollars to your cousin muhammad uh
and muhammad is in dubai
so you go to the local hawala which
might be in you know a bakery or the
meat cutters shop or wherever
and you say i want to send 50 to my
cousin muhammad in dubai he'll take your
fifty dollars
um he'll give you uh
i think it was a nine digit serial
number one i did i sent myself fifty
dollars just to try it out from uh from
abu dhabi to uh bethesda maryland was
the nearest wall i could find
so he gives me a nine digit number
i email the number to my cousin muhammad
he takes the number into his local
hawala in dubai says here's my my nine
digit number and he gets 48 out of the
fifty dollars the two dollars is for the
transfer fee it works we call it money
laundering right but for afghans dealing
with small amounts of money it works
it's the same system that the templars
put together that is the the same thing
yeah the basis for our public entire
banking system and and in these places
where you you have
don't have the infrastructure um you
know how do you get money to your your
to yourself in maryland for example you
know because so uh but
so these informal systems were existed
there were responsible parties for it
and now we're at a point where and i
don't know if we're gonna i guess we can
jump through right we spent a tremendous
amount of funds
training afghan the afghan military and
staff right afghan uh national security
forces and train and establishing border
border border patrols border a border
guard and all these other things formal
systems from a western perspective now
all that's gone
um and the taliban is stronger than ever
and maybe you can give a little bit of
an assessment from your perspective of
you know it's it's you know we have a
short time here but this summing up of
you know we treat we spent billions of
dollars on this training funding and all
this and and all this equipment and
ordinance but then and also establishing
these formal systems that should have in
in big air quotes established um a
uh
a modality for
the sustainability of this democratic
government yes but now um all that has
has failed uh and and we've seen the
probably the most explicit example of
a failure in state building uh so what
what is it from your perspective do you
think is you know and is
are are the the key areas that that you
think uh are leading to the taliban
strength because we're losing
and the holes that they're going to fill
um as i mentioned earlier i think
they're vast right there is no border
guard anymore so you know i don't know
what the arbiter are up to these days
but maybe they're going to reestablish
stuff but border crossings are free now
and the taliban's in complete control of
it so are taliban mechanisms going to
have more breadth and scope to them uh
than than they did back in the 90s uh
and do you think that um that any of
these systems uh informal systems will
re-establish themselves or do you think
it'll be a complete new uh taliban
overlay
i think it's going to be a combination
first of all um
boy where do we even start with
something like that how do we how did we
get here we we got here because of
corruption and tribalism
uh i remember in 2012
i mean there was the there was a report
in the new york times uh talking
as i say when you say corruption and
tribalism is it on the us side or is it
on the afghan side on the afghan
government side yes the the non-taliban
afghan government side okay
uh there was a there was a story about
dyncorp
dyncorp was charged with uh with
establishing and training a new national
police force the afghan national police
and so they they set up this huge
training facility they brought afghan
young afghan men from all over the
country from all the different tribes
and all the different regions that was
mistake number one
and what ended up happening one night to
make a long story short
is that
one of the recruits
poisoned a pot of stew that was being
served for dinner that night and he
killed about a dozen fellow recruits
well that night while the survivors were
sleeping he let four
members of the taliban into the
dormitory that was being used for
housing and they went bed to bed and
stabbed all the other recruits and
killed them
so this was a story for a day or two
days but to me it was it was a glaring
example of exactly what is wrong in this
country
in afghanistan
that
that the tribe was more important than
the nation
that
hazaras for example weren't supposed to
be working with pashtun
and northerners working with southerners
and it just wasn't going to work
and so you know when you hate your enemy
more than you love your country
it's doomed to fail nothing will work
if if that's you know the prevailing
the
feeling the prevailing belief right and
this is 2012 so 20. 2012 so we were
already 11 years into it yeah so so i
mean
so would you say
has that that change up to now
you know in the in the
when it comes to the tribalism what's
your thoughts on that no i think
tribalism has even strengthened in the
intervening years and i'll tell you what
i
for me personally i don't really care
who's who leads afghanistan if it's the
taliban well you know what it's the
taliban but i worry about
minorities in afghanistan i worry about
shia muslims i worry about the hazaras
specifically
when i was in afghanistan
back in i guess it was 2007
i met with a very senior hazara leader
and he made a point to me that was just
so interesting it stuck with me he had a
framed he had he had a shadow box quite
a large shadow box mounted on the wall
of his house and in it were all of his
judo belts from white to black right so
every time he earned a new belt he saved
it and ended up putting from white to
black and and i complimented him and i
said you're a black belt in judo and he
said i'm a fifth degree black belt
and i said that's that's really
incredible he said i didn't do it for
fun
i did it because hazaras are forbidden
from owning weapons in afghanistan he
said i'm a shia muslim i'm an afghan
like any other afghan and i'm forbidden
from owning a weapon he said i had to
have some way to protect myself
well that was under the afghan
government the one that's supposed to be
democratic and and supportive of human
rights and being supported and financed
by the united states what's it going to
be like under the taliban for religious
minorities like him that really worries
me you know religious and ethnic
minorities is tough i mean i think that
from from
the afghan perspective is that you know
there's always been a system of
collaboration cooperation amongst the
ethnic religious groups you know it's
just like it's like old school new york
you know everybody has their
neighborhood and uh you know and and
it's like lebanon before the civil war
yeah so
it actually worked it was tenuous but it
worked and you know and everybody has
their you know their their master place
of worship that you know and everybody's
doing this thing and so you know i i
when i was there in 2012 and i was at in
herat and i was talking about
the uh
you know how to how do we instill a
democracy and of course the the the the
uh the ultimate council was there you
know and they were they were you know
they're all
really close it's about 45 minutes from
the from the iranian border so you know
they're all sitting there you know like
this and and i just told them like oh
look
started off the conversation with you
guys have been done practicing democracy
longer than than than just about anybody
on the planet for thousands of years at
the sure and jurgen level you know the
village level right yeah and i said that
you know the problem is is no two
democracies are the same and uh and i
said let me give you an example uh
british democracy they have a house of
lords
in america
we would it's it's outrageous to us that
you'd have a hereditary body that
governs right yeah with like 2 000
people in it right right and they're all
psychos they're all sociopaths you know
so um and and so but so an afghan
democracy or american democracy is very
very different than a british democracy
so what is an afghan democracy going to
be right and it's up to you to do that
and the the
the the the the top guy the elder right
cut stands up and he says
you know
yeah you know john
is right you know and and uh and he goes
we we can develop our own democracy
because we know what we're doing right
and that approach i think was unique for
that moment um it never
i don't know if it didn't evolve in the
halls of the us government certainly but
it was one of those moments in time
where
i don't know if the afghans really had
the
opportunity to develop their own
democracy because it came from the top
down it was a cobble-centric
uh
very you know consolidated federalist
system it's highly centralized you know
i always say that uh the best system if
you're going to implement a federal
system it's like america before the
civil war you've got you know you've got
to have the uzbeks on the in the
northwest you've got to have the tough
geeks in the in the northeast you've got
to have the push tunes in the south
hazara somewhere in the middle um you
know the nurse donnie's you know they
got to do their own thing because you
know that's why those those are my
brothers and sisters over there you know
so you know you you've got to figure it
out in a in the right way um but
it was really a top-down government
during the karzai era it was very
centralized um and you know karzai was
appointing uh
mayors in towns and they're all flying
into
kabul and then flying back out
and um
and the challenge i think
now is that all those 20 years of ups
downs left and right
we have the dividend what are the
dividends we have contractors that made
a lot of cash we have
uh the us government that had that
implemented women's empowerment
programming and and uh and and a lot of
different um uh development initiatives
civil society initiatives but now all
that is is
is is it for not because the taliban now
is in charge and we know who they are
and what they're about yeah and and so i
know we're limited in time here so i'm
getting into the question of okay
are we dealing with a new taliban okay
and and and more of all taliban it
appears so because issues i think so you
know i gave myself this this is a
taliban that has been meeting with the
united states officially or unofficially
for several years now this is a taliban
that that ought to have learned its
lessons from 2000 and 2001
they're not stupid people
right they they've been in power and
they've been out of power and being in
power is better it's nicer so i i can't
help but to think
that this is not the taliban that is
going to rush to execute women in soccer
stadiums or to stone people to death for
listening to music or drag them behind
jeeps
as punishment for for some offense i
can't it may come to that again someday
but the taliban that we're looking at
right now i think has learned some
lessons over the last 20 years you know
there was an interesting uh point that i
i heard on one of the talk shows uh
yesterday morning saying that um that
something like
55 of the country was born after the 9
11 attacks right and so
that includes many members of the
taliban
yeah so perhaps they're not going to
make the mistakes their fathers made i
think
i think we should wait and see how this
plays out well it's interesting because
you know i i you know we hear all the
the reports
of of the taliban and i'm you know i i
was pat myself on the back because
we're trying to get people at the
airport and it was it was funny because
funny was but
that uh the us passport holders afghan
americans with us passports were come
were coming to the airport and the
taliban was letting them in
um
i had i and i i had gotten two reports
and i was talking to somebody and and
then roy reuters says this thing that
the taliban has orders from the top to
the down it says foreigners
you know spirit them to wherever the
hell they're going you know what i mean
and and get them there safe but do not
attack them which is uh it's it there's
it demonstrates some of the
sophistication particularly out of of of
the command and control that they have
um
over their their people but not only
that they look at the sophistication in
taking such territory in large part by
not firing a shot right it's not like
they they they put an army in the field
and they said we're going to just there
was a front line that pushed um i my i
had reports that talama of talent of
talib tellings actually embracing
kabulis and saying you know it's so good
to be back
and they were like is he attacking me is
he not attacking and they were confused
what's going on now that's not to say
like i've got a lot of people that are
in you know in hiding
and who are you know with american
passports or this or or or they were
involved in us u.s programming and so
forth and my you know where they said
we're limited time-wise
what are you what are your records right
now if you were going to talk to the top
on leadership uh you know because i
would say look
don't kill anybody right u.s government
engage the us government and and and
just put a freeze on any kind of
whatever it is you're thinking don't do
it yeah all right right now let's take
it some time to freeze and establish
some kind of communication so that the
people that work with the united states
who we cherish um and who they and and
their afghan citizens their afghan
people they have um the the peace of
mind to know that they have uh um are in
a safe zone for now um and we if we need
to get them out we can get them out but
if but we also need to establish some
some some kind of criteria so that our
national security is protected now that
we have a new regime so what's what's
your what's your you know your bluff
your bottom line up front i i think it's
twofold number one
we owe it to the people who worked with
us over the last 20 years to get them
and their families out we need to we
need to ensure the safety of the people
to whom we promised safety number one
number two we have to keep our line of
communications with the taliban open as
i said we've been negotiating with them
for a number of years mostly in doha we
need to keep those talks open even if we
don't immediately establish diplomatic
relations with the taliban we have to at
least be able to talk and to exchange
messages number three and i think this
is the most important is we need to
work very very closely with the chinese
on this because the taliban and the
chinese have excellent relations the
chinese have an exclusive contract to
mine rare earth metals in afghanistan
that we know from a dod report has a
value of one trillion dollars so the
chinese have a vested interest in a
stable long-term government in
afghanistan even if that means a
government headed by the taliban so if
any country has any authority in
afghanistan right now it's the chinese
and we need to engage with them to
ensure the safety of people inside
afghanistan yeah yeah i mean it's it's
uh
right now i think you know when you're
not talking it's a problem and you know
iran is is a perfect example of that if
you
have no idea what's going on because no
one's directly engaging the iranians so
if we can figure out you know so you
think you know should we have a
consulate in kabul should we establish
that right off the bat what do you think
you know what it would be very high risk
but i think at the same time it could
potentially be high reward so yeah you
know we we abandoned the us embassy
we're in the process of of getting the
last people out we destroyed all the
documents and all the equipment in the
previous few days but while we don't
need this massive compound like we have
now yeah i think we should have some
sort of a diplomatic presence in kabul
yes you know a building with a desk you
know yeah that's it that's all we need
you know and because at least there's
some kind of engagement in what's going
on and at least we can establish some
kind of trust i mean it's the the the
the trump government already recognized
yes
so it's so their their legitimacy is
already there and it doesn't matter even
if you say they're illegitimate they're
there now so
if we're going to not let this slide
into a dies isis situation with a and a
peppering of al qaeda we need to figure
out how to maintain relations and say
this is what's going on and you're right
it is when the china's interest um to
keep a stable country you know it you
know because they have they're the rare
earth elements and and uh and they have
other interests there as well and and
hopefully we have some interest i mean i
helped set up the ministry of minds
program with midas it's all gone you
know i helped out to the anp when they
had 600 generals retire i helped set up
the career path and the the master's in
plea in
master of public administration policing
and all this other stuff and all that
stuff's gone
you know it's just it's it's it's
flabbergasting you know to to to
his hand
um but
as my my his heart's been breaking this
past week and we've been pivoting now to
figuring out policy you know i think
that your insights are are appropriate
and and they they're helpful because
where where the who are the taliban what
are they about and where they're going
and we need to figure out as a country
how we're going to fulfill our
commitments to the afghan people and to
the american people and you know that's
security that's that's um
you know celebrating our wins but you
know right now while we're licking our
wounds we need to figure out you know
how we're going to deliver on our
promises and also
pay the path for the future
so john kiriakou i appreciate you taking
the time thank you so much good to see
you again yeah good to see you as well